so welcome to this Global Network
webinar
um my name is Alexander loshke and I
will be moderating this webinar today
and as one of the rare exceptions I'm
actually also one of the speakers today
my co-moderators uh panya you and Sean
Lovell
today we have with us Jonathan
challainer from the oecd
siddish kaushik from the World Bank and
Abdullah godzalov and myself from UNSC
who will present the new sdmx user Forum
which is hosted on the global Network
and also sdmx capacity development
initiatives
so we will introduce the semx Uso Forum
where users of sdmx are invited to ask
or answer questions find Solutions and
connect with experts and peers
The Forum is designed as a space to
generate ideas receive feedback as well
as to access information on case studies
and implementation scenarios
The Forum is open to all users
irrespective of their level of
experience and knowledge of sdmx
in addition to this we will also present
ongoing capacity development initiatives
and will engage with you our audience
to identify Your Capacity development
needs to better serve the scmx universal
community in the future
finally some first information about the
next stmx conference will be given which
will take place during the second half
of 2023
so let me now tell you a bit more about
my fellow speakers so Jonathan is the
community manager of the statistical
information system collaboration
Community or siscc
at the oecd statistics and data
directorate
Jonathan has led the implementation of
the dot stat Academy and online
self-play online self-paced learning hub
for stats Suite and data modeling in SDM
Max
it works as a senior data scientist in
the development economics data group of
the World Bank and leads several
multi-agency partnership initiatives
like the world integrated trade
Solutions
and the statistical data and metadata
exchange or sdmx and also the data
Innovation fund
Abdullah works in the statistical
capacity management section of the UN
statistics division UNSC
he is the statistics divisions focal
point on SDA Max a member of the SDA Max
Secretariat and coordinator of the
working group on sem X4 sdg indicators
and myself I also work in the
statistical capacity management section
of unsd I'm the developer of the UN
Global calendar of statistical events
and co-lead of the global Network and
its webinar series
as all speakers today I was part of the
team which brought the scmx user Forum
to life
um so before I hand over to sit uh
let me give you just some quick
indications how
things will work today
as usual we will first hear all
presentations before we will have a q a
session at the end
so feel free to write comments and
questions into the meeting chat at any
time during the Q a session if you
prefer you can ask the question yourself
we will then allow you to use microphone
and the camera
to generate a more interactive
atmosphere
but if you wish we can also ask the
question then for you
as always This Global Network webinar is
being recorded and will be made
available on the global network of data
officers and statisticians at yammer.com
unstats
so now I will hand over to sit sit the
floor is now yours please go ahead
your muted yeah I was yeah good morning
good afternoon everyone
uh
this presentation is a quick
introduction to sdmx so those of you who
do not know what SDM access or some have
some ideas to what SDM access are is
that this is just a quick overview of
what is DMX is all about and it's kind
of like
why what and how of sdmx
so going on like data challenges I think
you're all here in this presentation
because we all deal with data you
exchange data you disseminate data and
we bring in data from multiple sources
for our everyday work but some of the
common challenges that we Face are uh
when you pull data from different
organizations you get data in different
file formats you have to deal with
different API structure and once you get
the data you have to understand the data
that means you have to read code book
understand what the data is like when
you look at a number which are the
columns that identify the number and you
also run into issues like uh like if you
take two Excel sheet there will be
different column names for the country
or the age and
was more more importantly also the codes
are different so some will have like M
as male While others will have one as
male and fsp mail two spmail so you have
to do a lot of data massaging data
jugglery and uh roundabout work
workarounds to get data from multiple
sources before you can start using this
so all this leads to right like you can
see the details here so
and uh it leads to like a huge mapping
mess
and uh I think it's a problem in most of
the data shops that we have and the
solution is to standardize things so
when you look at uh that the travel
industry when you want to book your
flight ticket doesn't matter which
travel software you use or you call up
the airlines it's always the same
airport code that you booked to from and
to similarly the airline the the flight
that you fly in has got the same flight
number and it doesn't matter from which
corner of the world you're buying or
from brick system you're buying you
always end up in the airport that you
want to similarly when you trade on the
stock exchange like you doesn't matter
which brokerage you use you or which
software nowadays which app you use you
you can always buy yours the stock that
you want one of the most successful
standards is HTML where we can see where
you create a website and it doesn't
matter which operating system you are in
which web browser you are in you are
able to see the web page so sdmx is a
similar initiative sponsored by seven
International agencies to solve the
problem to of exchange of statistical
data and metadata
so now coming to the what what is sdmx
sdmx is an open standard for data and
metadata exchange and when you say an
open standard it is both for the
technical standards so which is kind of
your apis and the content standard so it
tries to have standardize both the
content that we get is exchanged and
also the way which machine to machine
communicate more importantly sdmx has
got a data and metadata modeling so when
you exchange your data not only you make
your data available via an API it also
helps users to understand uh the data
that they are consuming without having
to read too much of a code book like
assess if you are a programmer you will
be able to figure out okay which are the
columns which are not null which are the
columns which may be null and which are
the primary keys to identify the data
those kind of information you get so all
in all it enables machine to machine
coming community education and since its
Inception way back in the early 2000s it
has always been based on supporting open
source standard ID tools so it is like
you create a tool once and everybody can
they use the same tool
so ldmx has got three major components
this is going a little bit into the
weeds but it's still a 50 000 view uh 50
000 feet view so it's got the technical
specification which defines how the API
should be and other details around that
the data exchange mechanism then you
have the content oriented guideline
which tries to harmonize your content so
something like everybody calls country
with the same set of column names or age
or sex or everything else and here and
then there is a glossary created so that
we all speak the same line the same
language a good example is like when you
say football it's got a different
meaning in North America as opposed to
in the European continent or same thing
with a trolley with trolley in the US
and the UK means totally two different
things so the idea of the glossary is
like when we say a particular word if we
are all implementing as DMX we are all
speaking the same language and there is
no nothing last translation and the last
empire and the most important which I
think all of you should be
focused on is the tools the open source
tools there are like lots and lots of
tools available in sdmx and you can get
a lot of information on the HDMX website
so here is an example of how sdmx makes
life simple especially those of you who
are developers who are trying to pull
data from multiple apis and you end up
with writing like five or ten different
set of codes depending on the number of
organizations from which you're trying
to pull whereas with sdmx if you see the
call structures are all standardized so
all you need to change is the domain
from which you're pulling the data but
the rest of the process remains uh a
standard so once once you write a code
if you have to add a new organization
that says DMX compliant it's very easy
you just add in the configuration what
will your domain is and what the new
initial call structure is and you're
good to go
uh
sorry am I going back
uh content oriented guidelines so as I'm
as I said this is trying to like
harmonize the kind of data that we
exchange so everybody calls frequency is
a particular thing age in a particular
way and when you look at statistical
data unlike the travel industry or the
financial industry which had given it is
spread across multiple domains so you've
got like national accounts you've got
social you've got many other
things so so we are kind of uh using the
unece classification for uh defining the
various domains uh and then the cross
domain code list so this is more like
when you exchange codes like when you're
exchanging something like frequency so
everybody says agrees on a is annual Ms
monthly D is daily Etc so in this way we
eliminate a lot of mapping of data when
we exchange data and it becomes much
more seamless exchange of data so here's
a quick example of a cross domain
concept something like your which
repeats across statistical domains like
your frequency of data like whether it
is monthly data whether it is annual
data reference area is what we use for
country or region or sub-national and
whether the data is comparable or not so
if you see on the right you can see some
of the code harmonization for the
frequency code list
want to go into the details of this but
this is something which the sdmx group
takes care of so when you're drafting
you just take these code lists and
implement it
here is an example of the statistical
subject matter domain so you've got
demographic and social statistics
economic statistics
environment and multi-domain statistics
within them you got further subdivisions
but to a large extent this helps us
guide create domain specific code lists
and Concepts and also cross domain code
list and Concepts
now if you have to implement sdmx you
are a statistician and you want to
implement as DMX like many of these
terms like code list and Concepts may be
a bit uh
overwhelming but essentially all that
you need to do as a statistician in your
organization is to understand your own
data and provide to the
team implementing is DMX how to
interpret your data so here is an
example of an external data and as a
statistician all that you need to do is
say that okay country stock flow time
and the topic are necessary to identify
the observation out there like and if
you look at other things like unit
multiplier and unit uh these are needed
to further qualify your data so
essentially that's what you do and then
the team implementing is DMX and we have
a lot of capacity building activities
which my colleagues will be talking
later on will help you to adapt it but
once you adopt it then your data
exchange with other organizations and
even within your own Community will
become much more seamless and faster
so some of the key benefits of SDM
access it's an open internationally
agreed standard for exchange so as I
pointed out in the example of the data
API calls that you make it becomes very
simple and because the content is
standardized you don't have to do too
much of data massaging before you can
start using it so it's syntactic and
semantic interoperable so more like it
is more like when you pull a data not
only you get the data but you also are
able to get enough information as to how
to interpret the data as DMX is built on
the principle of reusable open source
tools so you don't have to invest a lot
of time and money into building tools uh
it does harmonization of statistical
Concepts and codes which I've been
talking about more importantly
versioning is very strong in sdmx so if
you want to maintain data versions you
have to maintain your technical standard
versions as the MX provides you a lot
and it helps you to have like if you
want to go back in time to see how your
data was it helps you a lot and all in
all it helps you to have timely
collection and dissemination of data and
metadata efficiently
thank you
thank you Sid for for this overview
before we continue with the next section
which is basically an introduction to
the semx user Forum I would like to ask
all participants to answer this little
question so what do you use sdmx for and
then you can choose between data
modeling processing integration data
dissemination data reporting or you can
say we do not use semx at the moment and
that you are exploring to use sdmx in
the future
so maybe
we can
we can have a please
answer those questions and we have the
results coming in
so just just yes you didn't see it it
didn't flash on screen uh click on the
polls yes
sorry it didn't come up on the screen I
wasn't aware it came up on my screen but
okay so in I think it should also be in
in the chat
so we have now and do you see the
results Jonathan
I can otherwise I can I can I can see it
Alex I think you have to submit your
response so 21 have said like so we have
got like 90 response so far and 21
person say they use for data modeling
processing integration uh 32 percent say
they're using for data dissemination 21
say they are using it for data reporting
eight percent have said they are not
using sdmx at the moment and 16 person
say we are exploring use of sdmx and by
the time I finished it there are 98
percent but 900 responses but the
percentages have not changed much
uh thanks so much Sid
um so uh this thanks for for to everyone
for answering this little poll we will
have two more questions uh later on so I
will start now uh with my section
presenting the stmx user form I will
share my screen
and
um
I hope you can see it now
so
I will give a short introduction to the
scmx user Forum in the next 10 minutes
so what what is the sdmx user for
so the semx user forum is an open and
inclusive online community to connect
and share knowledge on SDM X it's a
forum where you can ask questions
you can find answers to those questions
or you can provide it answers yourself
to questions which you think
you you can contribute something to them
you can also connect with experts in
peers from around the globe who work on
sdmx or with sdmx
the sdmx user forum is is hosted on the
global network of data offices and
statisticians
and because we are working with numbers
let me give you a few numbers
about the SMX user Forum so The Forum
has currently more than 250 members
the ratio of monthly active uses to the
total number of members of The Forum is
about 70 which is a very good value and
shows how active
the The Forum actually is
since the launch there were more than
120 messages posted and those messages
were read on average more than 70 times
so and what kind of questions would you
find on the sa Max use of arms so so far
they had in
1717 questions asked all were answered
in less than 48 hours usually it's
within a day but
so for sure within 48 hours
you will see here on the screen the
topics uh
uh
with which those questions were
classified
and some of the popular topics were sdmx
modeling
vtl and also
things like SC questions about semx in
general
I would like now to show you
the
stmx user Forum live so and I want to
show you also three examples of
questions so the first one
is on
sdmx sorry
let me switch to my other browser
okay
so the first one
is on
stmx modeling and so there was a
question about the attributes in a
typical DSD of sdmx so this is a
question posted by Dimitris uh posted
yesterday actually
and you can see at the bottom so several
people have already answered so Stratos
have provided an answer and Abdullah has
added on to that
you can also see that the question the
answer by Stratos was marked by the by
Dimitris as the best answer so this
functionality of showing the or taking
the best answer is something that the
person who is asking the question can do
or a moderator
so this is just one example
then we have for instance a question
about vtl
and
yeah here's a this was a question by
Nicholas posted earlier this month
where he has provided also some
data as an example
and you can also see that several people
have answered and then Nicholas has
reacted to it
so this is more or less the way it looks
yeah when you ask a question and what
will happen
so let me explain also how to join the
global Network and the scmx user Forum
very quickly so for that I will open an
incognito window just because I'm
already locked into
the um
Global Network so you would go to
yammer.com
you instead
all right and when you do that you would
see a screen like this
and you would provide your
email address
and preferably you would use your
work email address and then once you hit
sign up you will receive an email
and then there are like two steps more
which you need to do to basically finish
the sign up process
okay so this is how to join the global
Network and then let me maybe explain a
little bit more how to get there so
let's say you have joined the global
network but you don't know where to find
the sdmax user forum
in that case you can just type sdmx here
on the top left in the uh in the search
and the first hit should be the sdmx
user forum
there are two more groups related to
sdmx but which are private one is a
coordination group for the sdmax user
firm and the other one is a group bought
the preparation of the sdmx conference
so those are not public but the SMX user
form is open to everyone so what you
will see in the middle here is basically
the feed with the questions and answers
right
on the right hand side you will see some
more information about The Forum and
popular topics and also some
documents with uh additional information
about like the standard set of topics
and the usage policy
okay so and if you want to ask a
question then in the samx user Forum
that would happen here in the middle
at the top so there's several types of
posts you would choose a question pose
and say so this is my question right and
and you write a little bit there
for uh and explaining what your question
is you can also use bold face and italic
face if you want to you can uh
link to a web page if you want to
which I will not do now you can also
upload a file from your computer if you
want to by clicking on this and then you
select the file and you open it it will
be added to your question
please don't share any confidential
information because
you don't want to expose any individual
data of anyone
so once you have asked the question
[Music]
um
people can reply to a question like this
question by Dimitris you can click on
reply and I could then add
answer the question by Dimitris uh
providing an answer and posting it and
it will be visible to everyone
and then if I don't want to rep
ly to Dimitri's original question but
maybe to let us answer I can click reply
there
and if I scroll down you will see okay
now it says Alexander logic is replying
to Stratos right and so it becomes clear
to whom you are replying to
so this is a little bit an overview of
the sdmx user Forum
um I cannot go in to all the details I
just want to mention a couple of things
more and for that I will go back to my
presentation
um
so there is also a Yama mobile app which
you can use and I encourage you to
download it it has some additional
features it uh like uh for instance
upvoting of answers which is not
available on the website uh web browser
version
and
um
later on we will share those slides with
you uh
later on you can choose to download
those apps those are the QR codes to go
to the App Store of the
iOS or Android
so how to join the SMX user firm I have
already shared in the chat also a link
to the instructions
um so
please read through the instructions it
gives you really a step-by-step
explanation how to join
and
once you are at the scmx user Forum
don't forget to join also this group so
there's on the top right there will be a
button join group and when you click on
that you will receive notifications
from this stmx user forum
uh what else well there are a couple of
organizations uh where we know that
there are issues with joining uh joining
with a work email address
um
so if you are working for one of those
organizations uh please send us an email
and we can explain to you how to join
uh or directly join with your private
email address and inform us and we will
admit you then very quickly
in general we encourage work email
addresses but it's not always possible
for everyone
okay
just two more slides one is uh with a
slide with a couple of links uh
two important documents
we will share this later on with you
and then there's also a page what to do
if you encounter a problem joining the
stmx user forum
and that's it so that's my part of the
presentation today
thanks and let me unshare my screen
and give back to
now I hand over to Jonathan
Jonathan go at
Jonathan
it seems Jonathan has a connection
problem yeah so uh in that case
um what I want to do is to
um
Jonathan wanted to ask a second poll
question and I will launch that one now
um so have you undertaken any sdmx
training course during the last year
please answer that question
so if you want you can also go to the
chat the question should be there
yeah no worries no worries yeah you you
looked Frozen but I hope it works now so
if you have bandwidth problems maybe you
can switch off the video if you want to
um are you still here
ah no okay so uh we have now already 84
answers and uh most of you haven't done
any training during the last year on
sdmx so
um I would now maybe hand over then to
Abdullah who can give you a little bit
an overview of the
of what is available as training
opportunities in stmx over to you
thank you Alex let me share my
screen
can you see the presentation
Yep looks good okay thanks very much
okay thanks
um Alex
um uh so good morning good evening good
evening everyone and thank you for
joining us today
uh we are slightly behind the time so I
will uh run quickly through
um sdmx learning opportunities which we
have here today
if we're talking about
capacity building in general
um in the area of sdmx um
it has been provided by various agencies
by the sdmx sponsors of quest the seven
uh sponsors and also by other
International and National organizations
such as the ILO
the African Development Bank and Nation
Development Bank the UN Regional
commissions including unece una Clark
here in escap here in ECA
and of course UNESCO
all of them have undertaken you know
have offered training in sdmx and
Italian national statistical office and
that is
so
sometimes it's provided as part of
regular training programs in particular
eurostat or it can be provided as part
of specific projects which is more
characteristical of un agencies
it has been provided at Global events uh
particularly the HDMX Global conference
if you were at the last testimix in
person as DMX Global conference and
Budapest we had a large capacity
building program there we also provided
some capacity building
um in 2021 uh when the Conference was
held online
of course
um
we all know what hit is three years ago
in 2020 when we went into lockdown and
the in-person training became a luxury
unachievable luxury
so since the pandemic started for the
last three years e-learning courses have
increasingly become a focus
and we will talk about some of them now
so
the first training course I'd like to
talk about is the sdmx foundation a
learning course this is an introductory
course introduction to sdms its
development was led by the Asian
development Bank in cooperation with
unsd
and
social commission for Asia and the
Pacific as well as Statistical Institute
for Asia and the Pacific we work
together on this um
e-learning course it was finished about
a year ago
and it opened for registrations in March
last year and it run from March to from
late March to early May 2022.
the board for the training course where
people could
answer questions receive answers it was
provided
um
as part of a specially set up user form
which is why it was not available which
is why after the you know
the course closed it ceased to be
available
however now that
um
the sdmx user forum is up and dreading
support for that training course is
provided through the sdmx user forum and
therefore the Asian development Bank
kindly
uh made this training available on a
permanent basis
about a month ago
so
the module the training consists of two
modules module one is an overview and
business case which is important for
both
um
managers those who are trying to
understand how sdmx can help the
Enterprise but also technical experts to
understand what the business case is and
basically also how how to use the stmx
and module two
is
um
oriented towards the technical experts
and it does give an introduction you
know the introduction to the basic
concepts of sdmx with the information
the basics of the information model the
candid oriented guidelines and and
others
so
um
the course had a very high attendance
last year
over 400 people I think about 430 people
completed the course and received the
certificate
and now it is available
um
on a permanent basis so if you would
like to
learn if you are have heard about sdmx
but
don't really know what it is and how to
use it what it can be used for
then I think that this training can be
very helpful
another training course
um I wanted to introduce is the a
training course on sdmx for sdg
indicators
it was developed by unsd and the um
working group on SDM on sdmx for the for
sdg indicators and its objective is to
support the data exchange and
dissemination of a sustainable
development goals indicators
um
this e-learning course is um
intended for those who already have a
basic knowledge as DMX of sdmx and would
like to learn how to use the sdg data
structure definition and how to
establish LG data exchange and
dissemination
um so there is a prerequisite unlike the
previous one there is a prerequisite I
mean there is a prerequisite for this
training is a basic knowledge of sdmx
and uh
it is advisable that you take the sdmx
foundation course before taking the
training on sdmx for the sdgs so that to
familiarize yourself with the basic um
um
knowledge and in the tech wire a basic
understanding of sdmx
um the registration link is here it will
be announced at the sdmx user Forum
today so if you join the user Forum
today which are very much encouraged to
this is probably the first thing that
you will see
I will not go in detail about the dot
stat Academy learning courses because
Jonathan whose presentation is after
mine uh we'll talk about it in further
detail but that's that Academy is
growing very rapidly it has two learning
courses already available and it's
working on others the third that are
available are introduction to estimates
for data producers technical expert
studies
and the other one is Introduction to
sdmi structural modeling both very
useful and very important training
courses
and very briefly to talk about
um
the planned alerting courses the Asian
development bank is leading the
um development of
a very important alerting course on as
on a on the
as On sdmx Tools
this course will
um
present we'll provide an introduction
and Hands-On exercises for some of the
commonly used and sdmx tools and it's
working the the development is led by
the Asian development Bank in
cooperation with unsd ILO as cap and
Capp and other agencies those which are
which develop the tools
creation development backend you and SD
are also planning to develop later the
main specific learning course so we have
now won the main specific learning
course on sdmax for the sdgs but we're
also going to um Aviation Development
Bank with you know in cooperation with
unsd are also going to develop you know
planning to develop training for
National accounts um uh trade and others
and those that Academy as I mentioned is
working on
their own e-learning courses which
Jonathan will talk about in more detail
and this is it from me thank you
so I will start my presentation here
thank you Abdullah
um yeah we have a
we have some technical problems with uh
Jonathan
um connections so I don't see him in the
meeting right now so what I will do is
maybe I will first share our third and
last question
which is
uh about in what areas you would like us
to do more training in the future and
I'll do that right now
uh so in what areas would you like to
see more stmx training courses made
available and then you have the choice
between data modeling data processing
and integration
data dissemination data reporting and
you can select several options if you
wish
so please do that right now
and we have the results coming in
um so we're yes go ahead uh Alex
as we wait for Jonathan to join maybe
yes we should uh we can answer questions
if there are any
yep we can do that so but first uh let
me
yeah so
um
so there were now questions about
um sorry people were saying that they
would like to have training on data
modeling 23
data processing and integration 30 data
dissemination 25 and data reporting 22
so 84 people have answered and I saw
very briefly
Jonathan Jonathan are you back with us
yes can you hear me yes okay uh it's
just starting again sorry apologies for
that uh team's just shutting down
without warning
oh that's not good uh shall we try with
your presentation right now
so Abdullah has done his presentation it
would be now your turn yeah just let me
get this up
and then uh while we wait for Jonathan
bringing up the presentation uh just
another encouragement for you everyone
if you have questions please put them in
the chat and we will come to them in a
few minutes
okay go ahead Jonathan thanks
okay so hopefully you can see my
presentation and you can name it yes and
hopefully we're not going to have any
more technical issues on my side uh so
yeah so thank you uh for that and um
um I think it's quite timely we've
discussed this also because it seemed
like a vast number of people majority of
people
aren't actually or haven't taken courses
recently so
um and there is interest
um Abdullah did present a number of
these so I I will my presentation will
look at one particular initiative in
um focus on the dot stat Academy
um and also touched on a few other
initiatives from other organizations
that uh
um that are conducting estimates courses
um so
yeah so what is the Dutch Academy so um
the dot set Academy is a
self-paced online Learning Hub it's
providing today free online training and
resources to support capacity building
in the dotset Suites
but also which is a topic of the day XD
mix and data modeling for data producers
and data toolers so data tool as being
the technologists
um so who's behind this so the state
academy is initiative from the sacc so
this is a um Alex introduced us at the
beginning these disco information system
collaboration Community uh this is a
group of organizations that is
collaborating together since around 2010
um and having now grown to 16 members
you can see these members on screen so
quite diverse across a range of
statistical producing organizations from
International rational and central banks
and really our focus is on on delivering
Concrete Solutions to common problems
and this includes driving forward XNX
implementation
[Music]
the Workwear number of Partners so in
our Partnerships that we build we are
supporting standardization as I
mentioned in XT Max tools data modeling
and capacity development including some
of those Partners on the call today
um so the Dutch Academy is
um uh supporting learning paths and
trading needs as I mentioned data
producers and data toolers so data
produces the ones producing and managing
the data process uh modeling
um you know processing of the data and
dissemination of the data
um the content is really designed to be
engaging uh and and be more practical so
really sort of uh aligns to how you
would apply this in the real world with
real world scenarios and quiz based
activities and interactive exercises
the learning levels are designed also to
sort of build your Knowledge and Skills
over time so you have this sort of uh
goal if you want that you want to reach
um and the the idea and the way that the
courses are designed and
structured is really to help you reach
that goal uh whatever that my goal might
be
um just uh to sort of uh quote Alex also
as as we are uh statistical
organizations we do like numbers so
here's a few numbers from the academy
um so today we have uh we're just over a
year
um old on this and we have a 275
registered users uh 360 enrolled in in
across the different courses that we
have
um and today we have uh close to 180
certified Learners and we have a number
of resources uh around 100 resources
this isn't just courses this is also a
documents and um and materials videos
webinars and things like this that we
have online as well
um so today there are two uh courses
that are related to XD mix and and data
modeling so we have this introduction
course to actually mixed with data
producers this is really the basics so
if you're if you're looking to uh learn
about XNX for the first time or maybe
you just want a refresher or to sort of
really understand a bit more about the
business case and the
um and how economics is structured
building also on aspects that um Sid
introduced at the beginning this course
is really for you so start here and it's
also a prerequisite for the second
course which is uh the introduction to
academic structure modeling for data
producers so this course is a course
that would guide you through step by
step
modeling process it uses a tool called
The xmx Matrix generator this is an
Excel
macro workbook that really guides you
through that process helps you every
step of the way and will you know really
cover those elements to to get you into
the modeling and start to apply that
more practically in your daily work
and so yeah this this course is all
freely available these were authored by
David baraklaf who is uh chair of the
swg xmx as disc working group and also
leads the oecd modeling and migration
work on xdmx and data at UIC do
um also a nice thing at the end of it
you will get certificate of completion
so just to say thank you for taking the
course and and to show that you've
actually completed it um and and this is
available at the end once you've
completed all modules and passed
um Abdullah touched on this also in his
presentation so we we do have some
courses that are are coming uh this year
uh we have a vocabulary course actually
split into two parts
um uh the first one is really a
beginners so it's it's touching on the
the terms that are used within uh xdmx
that you need to understand uh to Define
your tables and the related processes
and then we have a second course which
will build on this for those who really
uh want to go further in their
understanding of academics terms um and
we'll start to touch on things such as
in reference romance data and and more
um we also have a very important course
that's coming later this year which is
about optimizing the user experience
um it's very important to understand
that data modeling is just an XD mix is
not just about exchange of data but it
can drive the dissemination and we saw
that also in some responses the way
people are using X makes the day into
simulation and it's very important to
understand that your modeling decisions
also have implications for how the user
consumes your data and how it's
presented in in your dissemination
environment
so for example in the dots test Suite in
the data explorer that we component we
have is very much xmx driven so how you
design how you constraint you know you
build your data views this is very
important to consider during that
process and this course will actually
allow and and give you the skills and
knowledge to be able to do that in a
confident manner
a few courses that are in the pipeline
but they're not there yet and this these
these have no set date but
um we're discussing internally about the
courses around reference and metadata
unit of measure which is also an
important topic and quite complex and
structural metadata governance so this
is also an important topic it's not
necessarily related to the modding the
next mix itself but it's uh it's very
important how you set up your governance
to support this work and modeling work
within your organization especially when
we think about harmonization and
building sort of common elements such as
common code lists across your
organization
[Music]
there are a couple other courses that uh
uh can mention from different partners
that we work with also you're a staff
for example have a three-day in-person
training it's held once a year
um this is on in their premises in
Luxembourg uh the links here so you the
slides will be shared afterwards and you
can go and and search yourself and
register if you wish I will also have a
course which is an online course uh
through their eCampus and again this is
available the links here so please go
and find out more and there is many more
we've probably not mentioned today
um and in fact this is a a initiative
this year in the extreme Secretariat to
gather all uh information related to the
xmx courses and trainings that are going
on across all the organizations and to
bring that together and and to sort of
try to build a more
um sort of coordinated effort and
listing of these courses
this leads me to my next slide which is
around you know what what about an
Easter makes academy uh you know each
organization is producing nice courses
and there are many things going on uh so
we need to think about how we bring this
together and this is something as I
mentioned we're looking at doing
um and and building on the expertise we
have for example like the xmx user forum
is Alex presented today is a very
important initiative where we're
allowing uh you know enabling access to
experts to respond
um how can we build on that how can we
also build uh you know on the existing
trainings and aggregate those in a way
that's more easier to to access for for
users
um so yeah this will more to come on
this and uh between now and then uh
there'll be more engagement with the
community and and also gathering
information to to report back and also
have
um very likely the global conference
capacity building or capacity
development activities that will take
place it will take place in the later
half of the year the exact date is to
come and the host country is being
um and location of that is to be
confirmed uh shortly and this will be
shared once uh once ready by the
excellent secretary so I'll stop there
and thank you for your attention and you
can reach us also on these different
content points thank you
thank you
thanks very much Jonathan for this I'm
actually trying right now to
un basically give everyone the
opportunity to
unmute themselves and ask questions a
little bit struggling with that me teams
changes the setup of the
settings every now and then and now I
cannot find them nevertheless if you
have questions please write them into
the meeting chat right now and we will
address them
[Music]
um
so we have
yeah uh Matt Haven I see your hand up
but I I cannot uh unmute you
so maybe you can write it into the chat
until I can mute yours
so please write the question in the chat
if you have one
okay my colleague says he has a lot mics
and cameras so okay
please raise your hand now if you want
to ask a question and then uh
uh yeah Matt having can you please go
ahead
um hi uh hello everyone this is a really
good presentation
uh I just want to say that uh you know
uh has that any any documentation
requests coming from the community
because uh we we have been having a lot
of API upgrades actually per version so
are we pointing out Deltas you know a
point one has this particular thing
point two has this particular thing and
you have to give back Port supporting
that sort of situation uh this is
basically a software level uh on a
research basis I wanted to know like you
know are we giving you know a graphical
interface like you know Swagger has this
particular interface but doesn't have a
documentation so it becomes really
difficult for the gentleman who is
producing things it's uh you know to
have this particular thing so are we
pointing out uh such Solutions uh in the
sdmx Forum thank you
thanks
yeah uh Abdullah you have your hand up
yeah go ahead yes thanks very much for a
question about Poland I think it it's
the perfect question to ask at the sdmx
user Forum uh it's a bit too much to uh
to answer that in detail as we speak uh
but please join the user Forum please
ask that questions and I assure you that
you will have a detailed answer
yeah uh I will also share the link and
to the instructions in a minute again
um so we already are a little bit over
time but we had also a couple of
technical issues so we can still take a
couple of questions
please don't be shy raise your hand I
saw another hand earlier
but I don't see it right now
so
um
Maybe
I can ask also one question
um so so Jonathan and Abdullah you you
shared a lot of different
training courses there so
um you will also share this information
in the semx user forum is that correct
right so you will share the links where
to find everything and so on
maybe you can say a little bit about
that and
yeah go ahead
yeah just very quickly
um the sdmx foundation course has
already been announced by the Asian
development Bank um the announcement is
that the sdmx user forum and um
on the
um
sdmx sdg learning course it will be
shared today
right now
great thank you
um
yeah I just put a link in my chat just
to the academy so I we do Post in the
user form as well when new courses are
available and updates to courses are
available so yeah
yeah yeah also Michael Daniel Shetty has
posted a link uh to the sdmx sdg
learning course in the chat so if you
want to jump there right away uh you can
do it right now thanks Daniel
great
so any any other questions
we can take them now or if you want you
can also reach out later on to us so
either
preferably on the global Network as the
question there we will share the slides
and the recording there if you have
um issues with joining the global
Network please let us know that normally
it's a relative really smooth experience
but in some isolated cases there can be
issues so please reach out we don't want
to lose anyone on the way
um
yeah and I don't see any additional
questions so this could be a very good
sign means that we covered everything
people wanted to know
um I hope let's assume this is the case
otherwise
please raise your hand now
and if there are no questions
considering that we're already like
three minutes over time
I see another question by Matt Heyman
but hey
foreign
I was just wondering are we pointing uh
this stmx usage for sdg Summit because
uh respective Chief Antonio Gutierrez
has been talking about uh it for some
time thank you
cheers
thanks
so scmx for the sdgs uh
the question
yeah I'll take that one
um the uh sdmx uh framework for the uh
sdmx for the sdg indicators it was
developed by a working group on on sdmx
for the sdg indicators which was
established by the interagency and
expert group on sdg indicators so the
reports by the working group as well as
other working groups like for example on
geospatial information and other working
groups established by the iig sdg
they're going to all the Secretary
General reports on sdg data sdg
indicators and progress on the sdg
monitoring so they are part of it
they're submitted to their statistical
commission and then from there go to
Echo socket I just
okay thanks so I guess uh we will wrap
up now so but before you go please
um
turn on your camera if you want to
switch on your mic and then I would say
uh give especially at the other speakers
a big round of applause thank you
please join me
Alex we can't see you
thank you
thank you all right
thanks everyone for joining This Global
Network webinar and see you next time
for the next Global Network webinar we
will have one in about two weeks time or
regarding the world data Forum which is
coming up in April
so thanks for joining and see you soon
thanks everyone
thank you thanks very much bye
thanks go
thank you